Today's כ"ה *Kaf Heh* we pick up on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
right after the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, and the משנה mishna *Mishnah* had
listed ten or eleven—well actually, see it's an interesting debate—ways in which
there are higher levels between קודש Kodesh *Kodesh* and תרומה Terumah, *Trumah*.
So we're continuing to list these various levels and stratifications,
primarily the משנה mishna *Mishnah* is focusing in difference in terms of
how different things are to be treated, you know, חולין chullin *Chullin*,
מעשר ma'aser? *Ma'aser*, קודש Kodesh. *Kodesh*, תרומה Terumah? *Trumah*, תרומה Terumah *Trumah*,
קודש Kodesh. *Kodesh*, etc. But as we've seen, it also winds up
translating into creating different groups of people, which is going to be
ultimately where the משניות Mishnayot *Mishnayot* are going in terms of how
that gets effaced during the רגלים *Regalim*. So let's take a look
though at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to
look through these one by one. And the first one was about
being טובל tovel כלים *tovel kelim* in the מקווה *Mikvah*, that for
תרומה Terumah, *Trumah* you can put כלים *kelim* within כלים *kelim*, vessels
in vessels, so you've got a lot of different, let's say, bowls
of different sizes, or the same size or whatever, but let's assume
different sizes. You've got different bowls or you've got different pots, you
know how they sometimes come stacked one in the other, and can
you put them all in the מקווה *Mikvah* at once? So by
תרומה Terumah *Trumah* you can, and by קודש Kodesh, *Kodesh* you cannot.
So let's see what that is about. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says the following: בקודש מאי טעמא mai ta'ama, לא *Bakodesh mai ta'ama
lo*? Why can't you do this for—if you're immersing it for the
purpose of using it for קודש Kodesh, *Kodesh*? By the way, we'll
see later what would you use this for in terms of קודש
Kodesh *Kodesh*, like what are you going to—like if you're a כהן
Kohen *Kohen* perhaps you could use it to cook the meat in,
that would be one example, or even if you're not a כהן
Kohen *Kohen*, if you're going to bring a שלמים *Shelamim* you could
use it as a pot to cook the meat in. It will
also, as we'll see, be vessels that you could use to bring
the wine and the oil that comes along with קרבנות korbanos *Korbanot*.
So that would be a—another type of a use you would have
for vessels that would be קרבן korban *Korban* related. Again, I guess
if you're a כהן *Kohen* or you know you could also be
the plates that you're going to be eating on and so on,
although those normally wouldn't necessarily have things to put one inside of
the other. Anyway, בקודש מאי טעמא לא *Bakodesh mai ta'ama lo*? So
אמר רבי אילא Amar Rabbi Ila, משום שכובדו של כלי keli חוצץ
*Amar Rabbi Ila mishum shekivedo shel kli chotzetz*. Very simple reason which
would have occurred to me, anybody who's bought כלים *kelim* to the
מקווה *Mikvah*, you know, you separate out the כלים *kelim* because you
don't want one to be weighing on the other and get—and preventing
water from getting between the two. The weight of the כלי kli.
*kli*, you know, one weighs—you know, the inner one is—stay—it's—its weight keeps
it attached to the outer one and therefore the water does not
get between. So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says: One minute. והא מדקתני
סיפא משום חציצה, chatzitza הני לאו משום חציצה chatzitza *Veha midekattani seifa
mishum chatzitza, hani lav mishum chatzitza*? But one minute, we're going to
see another distinction between קודש Kodesh. *Kodesh* and תרומה Terumah *Trumah* that
also deals with greater scrupulousness or greater concern around חציצה chatzitza *chatzitza*
issues,
and if we have a different one that's based on that, presumably
you wouldn't have, if you have only a very finite small number
of things that are your distinctions, you wouldn't have two that are
really variations of higher concerns of חציצה chatzitza, *chatzitzas*. Presumably you would
have conflated them. So where do we see that there's a later
one that's going to be about a חציצה chatzitzah *chatzitza* concern? So
מדיקתני סיפא *midekattani seifa* because we taught at the end—מדיקתני סיפא *midekattani
seifa* because we taught at the end: לא כמידת הקודש מידת התרומה
*Lo kemidat hakodesh midat hatrumah*, קודש Kodesh, *Kodesh* is not like תרומה
Terumah *Trumah* the following way, שבקודש מתיר ומנגיב ומטביל *Shebakodesh matir umangiv
umatbil*, by קודש Kodesh *Kodesh* if you have a garment that you
need to immerse, you first undo any knots in the garment and
then you dry it off and then you immerse it, so presumably
that's to ensure that the water gets on all
surfaces. ובתרומה קושר ואחר כך מטביל *Uvatrumah kosher ve'achar kach matbil*, and
by תרומה Terumah. *Trumah* you can even tie it first and then
immerse it and you don't have to worry, you can assume that
the water will get into it. So there you see and that,
if anything, is a bigger concern, asked me, water getting into a
knotted garment. So and there we anyway have a distinction, so presumably
we wouldn't have it as two separate things based on the same
reason, based on the same type of concern. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says: No. רישא reisha וסיפא משום חציצה chatzitza, *Reisha veseifa mishum
chatzitza*. There could be two different things that are both because of
heightened concerns of חציצה chatzitza *chatzitza* by קודש Kodesh *Kodesh* over תרומה
Terumah *Trumah*. וצריכא *Utzricha*, you need to list them separately, one is
not inferable from the other. דאי אשמעינן רישא *De'ee ashmeinan reisha*, had
it just told the first case, הוה אמינא היינו טעמא דלקודש לא
*hava amina hainu ta'ama delakodesh lo*, here's why by קודש Kodesh *Kodesh*
purposes you can't, משום כובדו של כלי kli, *mishum shekivedo shel kli*,
because there's literally a weight of
an inner—inner vessel is weighing down and preventing water from getting on
the surface that's, you know, the between the two. אבל סיפא דליכא
כובדו של כלי kli. *Aval seifa deleika kivedo shel kli*, but in
the end where it's not about a weight of a vessel, אימא
לקודש נמי לא הוי חציצה lo havi chatzitza *eima lakodesh nami lo
hevei chatzitza*. I would say that maybe it wouldn't be a problem
and maybe although something is knotted, you know, if you're dealing with
a type of a garment—well garments are porous, right? Garments absorb water.
So you could say, all right, it's knotted, but the—you know, if
the garment whatever happens will be the water will get absorbed and
it soaks in, so maybe there's no issue there, and maybe that
should not be a concern even by קודש kodesh, *Kodesh*. The weight
of like a metal vessel or pottery that's one against the other
will really prevent any water from getting there. So therefore I wouldn't
have necessarily applied it. ואי אשמעינן סיפא *Ve'ee ashmeinan seifa*, and had
you just told me the case about the garment, הוה אמינא היינו
טעמא דלקודש לא *hava amina hainu ta'ama delakodesh lo*, here's why that
it's not that you can't do it for... for קודש kodesh. purposes,
משום דקטרא במיא הדוקי מהדק mishum d'kitra bemaya hiduki mehadek because a
knot gets even tighter when you immerse it in water, right? So
as we all know that'll happen, right? It'll be even tighter and
harder to undo and maybe therefore harder for the water to get
into it. אבל רישא דמיא אכלי מצפו Aval reisha demaya achlei matzpu
but if we're dealing with two vessels, one inserted in the other,
so what will happen? The water will cause the inner vessel to
float. It'll get, you know, it'll cause it to, you know, to
sort of rise up. So therefore מצפו ליה למנא matzpu leih lemana
it'll cause the vessel to float up. So לא הוי חציצה chatzitzah
maybe I shouldn't be concerned. צריכא Tzricha you need to tell me
both. Okay, so basic answer is yes, there are two different levels
of, they are both concerns of חציצה chatzitzah which we're more scrupulous
about by קודש kodesh, than by תרומה, Terumah, and they're not inferable
one from the other and they are two different and they are
two different concerns. And by the way, because of these reasons, right,
the obvious question should be: one minute, these seem like very reasonable
concerns. Why are you allowed to do it for תרומה? Terumah. Why
aren't we concerned for תרומה Terumah of these things? So the גמרא
Gemara has already sort of planted the basis for the answer, that,
you know, yes, on one hand they are legitimate concerns. On the
other hand, you know, you can say that normally it'll be taken
care of. You dunk something in the מקוה, mikvah, naturally the inner
כלי will rise up. You dunk a garment in the מקוה, mikvah,
naturally it'll get soaked. Okay, so those are, so presumably those explanations
are why it works for תרומה, terumah, but nevertheless we're extra scrupulous
for קודש. kodesh, And yes, those are two basic חציצה chatzitzah reasons.
Those are, they're basically two different things that are based on the
same reason of חציצה chatzitzah concern. That's explanation number one. אמר רבי
אילא, Rabbi Ila so the גמרא Gemara now says, רבי אילא לטעמיה.
Rabbi Ila l'ta'ameih. Now by the way, רבי אילא Rabbi Ila, who
explains that these are basically the same reason is going according to
another position of his. What's his other position? דאמר רבי אילא אמר
רבי חנינא בר פפא עשר מעלות שנו כאן. De'amar Rabbi Ila amar
Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa eser ma'alot shanu kan. There are ten levels,
there are ten distinctions here. Now if you count, there are really
eleven. Okay, and what we're saying is that by saying two of
them are based on חציצה, chatzitzah that is allowing him to turn
his eleven into ten by conflating two and saying that they're variations,
so to speak. Let's just quickly count them, okay? So to remind
you about what the משנה Mishnah, said. Number one, vessels in vessels.
Number two,
that when part of a vessel becomes טמא tamei with a rabbinic
טומאה, tumah, does the entire vessel become טמא tamei or only that
section? The inside, the outside, the handle, and so on. Number three,
if you're carrying a מדרס, midras, a seat of like a זב,
zav, and you're carrying תרומה terumah on your other shoulder there, does
the תרומה terumah become טמא? tamei? Number four, the garments of people
that eat תרומה terumah are considered מדרס midras for people who eat
קודש. kodesh. Number five are
this thing about undoing the knots in the garments before putting it
into the מקוה. mikvah. Where are we?
Number six, if you finish a vessel, even if a vessel is
uncompleted and completely, you know, no טומאה tumah has come in touch
with it, it's coming straight out of the potter's oven, nevertheless before
using it for קודש, kodesh, you need to put it in the
מקוה. mikvah. Number seven, a vessel if you have like apples in
a bowl, they're all considered one unit. The bowl combines them for
קודש, kodesh, not for תרומה. trumah, Number eight, קודש kodesh, goes up
to four level derivative, תרומה trumah, only three level derivative. Number nine,
if one of your hands becomes טמא, tamei, the other is not
for תרומה, trumah, but it is for קודש. kodesh, Number ten,
where are we?
Oh, if food has never become in contact with liquid and therefore
is not susceptible to טומאה, tumah, nevertheless you still have to wash
your hands for קודש, kodesh not for תרומה. trumah. And number eleven,
that the אונן onen and somebody who has brought a קרבן korban,
to end a טומאה tumah process still has to go to the
מקוה mikvah for קודש kodesh. purposes, not for תרומה truma purposes. So
there you have eleven, but he said ten. So the point is,
he by conflating the two, numbers two and number five, no, number
two and yeah, I think it was number one and number five
because number one was the vessel in vessel, number five was the
knotted garment, he's turned his eleven into ten. Okay, so that's רבי
אילא לטעמיה דאמר רבי אילא אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא עשר מעלות
שנו כאן. Rabbi Ila l'ta'ameih de'amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi Chanina bar
Pappa eser ma'alot shanu kan. There are ten, not eleven. And not
only is he saying there are ten, and but he does then
also explain that they're grouped conceptually differently. חמש ראשונות בין לקודש בין
לחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש. Chamesh rishonot bein l'Kodesh bein l'chullin shena'asu
al taharat ha-Kodesh. This was the issue that also came up yesterday.
What is the status if you always eat your חולין chullin? as
if it were a קרבן, korban? as if it had the קדושה
kedusha of a קרבן? korban, What status applies to that food? Does
it get treated like קודש kodesh, for in terms of its own
susceptibility to טומאה tumah and also in terms of the degree of
care that you become obligated
to treat it with? And also what's your status vis-a-vis that food?
Are you like somebody who keeps קודש kodesh or somebody who only
keeps חולין? chullin So all of those are the questions. Okay, so
he says the first five are בין לקודש
בין לחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש. bein l'Kodesh bein l'chullin shena'asu al
taharat ha-Kodesh. Those three. stringencies would apply whether it's real קרבנות korbanos,
or whether you're dealing with חולין chullin but you're treating it with
the level of קדושה kedusha of as if it was a קרבן,
korban, so those first five stringencies would apply. אחרונות, achronos, the last
five stringencies, לקודש אבל לא לחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש, l'kodesh aval
lo l'chullin s'na'asu al taharas hakodesh, only apply to real קודש, kodesh.
not to חולין chullin that was just treated as קודש. kodesh, So
what's the difference? So the first thing, by the way, תוספות Tosafot
points out is that this presumably is assuming that חולין שנעשו על
טהרת הקודש לאו כקודש דמי, chullin s'na'asu al taharas hakodesh lav k'kodesh
dami,
because the statement כקודש דמי k'kodesh dami is categorical. If you're of
the opinion that if you treat your חולין chullin, like קודש, kodesh
they're like קודש, kodesh, then that means for all הלכות halachos and
you don't have to distinguish. For everything it's treated as if it
was קודש. kodesh This is the position that generally it's not. Maybe
it's treated like חולין, chullin maybe it's treated like תרומה, truma but
generally it's not treated as קודש, kodesh and nevertheless for the first
five stringencies we apply those five. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
טעמא, why are we more stringent for the first five? חמש קמייתא
דאית להו דררא דטומאה מדאורייתא גזרו בהו רבנן בין לקודש בין לחולין
שנעשו על טהרת הקודש. chamesh kamaisa d'is l'hu drara d'tumah m'de'oraisa gazru
b'hu rabanan bein l'kodesh bein l'chullin s'na'asu al taharas hakodesh. The first
five that are rooted in a biblical טומאה tumah that somehow are
connected to a sphere where there's a biblical טומאה tumah concern, so
those will apply even to חולין chullin that are done על טהרת
הקודש. al taharas hakodesh. Even if that חולין chullin, does not normally
have treated with the same level as קודש, kodesh we will apply
the first five stringencies to it. בתרייתא, basraisa, the last five, דלית
להו דררא דטומאה מדאורייתא, d'lais l'hu drara d'tumah m'de'oraisa, that do not
have a connection to biblical טומאה, tumah, גזרו בהו רבנן לקודש, gazru
b'hu rabanan l'kodesh, so those last five stringencies only apply to real
קודש, kodesh? real קרבנות, korbanos, or real things sanctified with the same
קדושה kedusha as a קרבן, korban, but לחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש
לא גזרו בהו רבנן, l'chullin s'na'asu al taharas hakodesh lo gazru b'hu
rabanan, but not for things that are not real קרבנות, korbanos. even
if they're treated as if they were קרבנות. korbanot Now how is
it that the first five are linked to a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern
and the last five's not? Let me just tell you that if
you were figuring out yourself you would not have normally come to
that conclusion, that the first five are somehow more stringent than the
last. One thing תוספות Tosafot has to say in order to make
sense of it is that the first five are not only linked
to a דאורייתא de'oraisa but a דאורייתא טומאה de'oraisa tumah that could
apply to חולין, chullin. whereas the last five are linked to טומאות
tuma'os that might not be relevant for חולין. chullin. So just to
say it over quickly, the two concerns we've been dealing with about
dunking something in a מקוה mikvah that obviously connects to a can
connect to a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern, is if there's חציצה chatzitzah? that
prevents a legitimate immersion even מדאורייתא. m'de'oraisa. Okay.
The other one about the the inner and outer part of a
vessel and so on, so although that's only about a rabbinic טומאה
tumah that we would chop up a vessel between the inside and
the outside and the handle, but it's but it's applying to טומאות
tuma'os that as we'll see later are based on rabbinic טומאות tuma'os
related to liquids and the reason we're more strict about those טומאות
tuma'os is because they are they are based on a concern of
like the spit and other types of fluids that come from a
זב zav and a זבה zavah and so on. So again that
seems a little far-fetched because the whole טומאה tumah is דרבנן, d'rabanan,
this whole idea of dividing up a vessel into different sections is
a rabbinic type of an idea, but nevertheless because fluids טומאה tumah
are linked in a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern of real דאורייתא de'oraisa fluids
that are טמא, tamei, that's considered in this list of connected to
a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern. Like I said you would not have come
to this conclusion yourself. Number three, wait, let me just go through
it. Number three, carrying a real מדרס, midras, carrying a real אב
הטומאה av hatumah on your shoulder with something else, obviously there there's
a could be a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern that somehow those two could
come in contact. Number four, the idea that the garments of somebody
that eats תרומה truma. is considered a מדרס, midras, is linked to
a concern that a זב zav or זבה zavah more particularly his
wife who's a נדה niddah would sit on it and so on.
So there's a possibility of some טומאה דאורייתא tumah de'oraisa going on
there. And we mentioned the issue about the knotted garments. And then
number now number five is
vessels that are made, even if there's nothing comes in contact with
them you need to dunk to a מקוה, mikvah, the גמרא Gemara
will say because there's some concern that in the process of being
made maybe something טמא tamei came in contact with it. Of course
that this sounds like a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern, everything is based on
some some amorphous and abstract concern, right? To say that there's a
דאורייתא de'oraisa standing behind all of this is hard exactly to see.
And why the last five are more lenient is not so obvious,
right? So for example,
the idea that a vessel combines everything inside of it, you know,
if it touches real טומאה tumah is does not seem like something
that's so out of some ambit of a דאורייתא de'oraisa concern. The
idea that טומאה tumah goes down to three levels by תרומה truma
and four levels by קודש, kodesh also we'll see there's a דאורייתא
de'oraisa parallel to that. That's why תוספות Tosafot has to say but
it doesn't exist by חולין. chulin
If one hand is טמא tamei the other is not, that already
the idea of טומאת ידים tumah yadayim is purely rabbinic.
Dry food, to become to have to wash your hands before dry
food, food that never came in contact, one could say okay so
it never came in contact with liquid, it'll never be biblically טמא.
tamei. And the idea of the אונן ומחוסר כפורים onen um'chusar kippurim
also there's no real biblical category for them as well for them
to become טמא. tamei. But again, it is, believe me, it is
not so obvious. Some of the things in those last five you
could easily have said are connected indirectly to a biblical one, some
of the first ones in the first five you could have said
are not so biblically connected. Anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara saying.
That's why we somehow have some of these תוספותים tosfotim that makes
it a dash shorter, because how exactly that makes sense is not
so transparent. Yes.
Just a question, the word גרירא grira that you used over there,
is that like גוררת, goreret, is that like?
Yeah, so there's a, yeah, גרירא grira means like some type of
a
vestige, or some type of a, I guess גוררת, goreret, I mean
תוספות Tosfot says like סרך srach is the word that תוספות Tosfot
uses elsewhere to describe what גרירא grira means. So you're right, סרך
srach is like something adhering, so something maybe dragging, but some right,
some clinging, some adherence of some of some type of a concern.
קשיא. kashya. Yeah, exactly, exactly. I'm interested, how does the English translate
the word גרירא? grira?
Some, I'd say like the ambit of, something derived, but not exactly.
Concern. Concern, okay. Nice abstract word. All right, so anyway back to
the גמרא. Gemara Okay? So we somehow divided the first five and
the last five, although exactly the logic is not so clear, I
mean the assertion about what it is is clear, but how the
specifics fit is not so clear, and we've also said that numbers
one and number five are the same because they're and therefore we
have five and five and not six and five. Okay.
רבא אמר מדיסיפא הוי משום חציצה. Rava amar mideiseifa havei mishum chatzitza.
Now רבא Rava says no, since the issue of the knotted clothes
is a concern of חציצה, chatzitzah רישא לאו משום חציצה. reisha lav
mishum chatzitza. The first part about one vessel in another vessel is
not a חציצה concern. ורישא היינו טעמא, ureisha hainu taama, here's the
reason for the first part of the first thing that you can't
do, one vessel in another. גזירה שלא יטביל מחטין וצינורות בכלי שאין
בפיו כשפופרת הנוד. gezeira shelo yatbil machatin vetzinoyot bikli she'ein befiv keshfoferet
hanod. Let's say you want to go and dunk in your מקוה
mikva some needles. Okay, now how are you going to dunk needles
in a מקוה? mikva? Like nobody's ever done that because you only
have to for us dunk things in a מקוה mikva that you're
going to use for cooking. Okay, but let's say you wanted to
go ahead and dunk needles because any type of thing, or like
tiny little I don't know toothpicks and these types of things. How
are you going to do it without it all sort of getting
lost? Fall to the bottom. So you're going to put them in
a basket. You're going to put them in a vessel. But you
put them in a vessel, it's going to float out of the
vessel, right? They're not weighted, it's like in our מקוה mikva here
you got one of these like plastic laundry baskets, right? So if
your stuff is heavy it goes to the bottom and then you
pull it up and all the water runs out. Wonderful. But try
doing that with needles, right? They won't necessarily fall to the bottom
and you'll lose them. So what you'll want to do is, you'll
want to put them inside let's say a jug with a small
hole so that the water will go in and the needles won't
be able to go out and float out, and that's how you'll
do it and then they won't go to the bottom of the
מקוה. mikva. The only problem is, is that then the needles in
the jug that are like you have the water- ah you see,
because you gave me a whiteboard, I have the whiteboard behind me,
I'm going to use it. So if you've got your jug in
there, right, and you've got your needles here and the water comes
in and you're in the מקוה mikva and the water's here, okay,
and here's the water of the מקוה. mikva. So are they considered
to be in the מקוה mikva water? Is the water in here
considered a continuation, like or one unit with the מקוה mikva water
that surrounds it, or are they just, you know, if you had
a stopper in here, even if they'd be in water, it wouldn't
be considered part of the מקוה mikva water. So how big does
this opening have to be in order for this to all be
considered one unit of water and that they're in the מקוה mikva
water?
I wouldn't think it would make
a difference as long as it's connected. Well, you'd be wrong. So
the answer is that it has to be- it has to be
a שפופרת הנוד. shfoferet hanod. It has to be the width of
a שפופרת shfoferet is like a tube, a straw that you would
use for
a נוד nod is like a leather, what's it called, not
skin, right, like a water flask. And so that tube is basically
the width of two fingers. So it's got to be a circle
that's basically two fingers
diameter of two fingers, and then the water's all considered part of
the מקוה mikva water. Otherwise, it's מקוה mikva water that got into
the vessel but it's no longer connected to the water of
part of the
מקוה. mikva. Like for that pipe, like you
know connecting the
water? Yes, yes.
I mean that's what one of those big תוספות tosfot is about
is about- this is a very
relevant הלכה halacha that if you've got the basic way we operate
our current מקואות mikvaot is, right, how do you do it so
that you don't have to stay with the same dirty water every
time? So you've got here your- you've got on your roof your
thing that collects your rain water and brings it down, here's your
rain water. Okay, and it brings it down and it- into this
בור bor and this is the בור מי גשמים bor mei geshamim
okay and that water doesn't change and then you've got here the
מקוה mikvah that people actually go to that gets you know nice
fresh water pumped into it and this is all מים שאובים mayim
she'uvim
hopefully with chlorine
with chlorine or whatever and that's all מים שאובים mayim she'uvim right
because it's not good water it's drawn water it gets pumped in
and you change it regularly and what you do is you have
a connection between these two and since this is connected to a
kosher מקוה mikvah it itself becomes kosher this has forty סאה se'ah
this is fully kosher on its own this connection allows this to
be considered part of this מקוה mikvah and this has to be
a שפופרת הנוד shfoferet hanod it has to be a pipe that's
that width and then it's considered to be all the same water
so that's the same principle that allows that basically informs our basic
construction of מקואות. mikvaot. Okay so let's take a look. So רבא
Rava said
רבא אמר מדסיפא הוי משום חציצה רישא לאו משום חציצה ורישא היינו
טעמא Rava amar midseifa havei mishum chatzitzah reisha lav mishum chatzitzah u'reisha
hainu ta'ama here's the reason of the רישא גזרה שלא יטביל מחטין
וצנורות בכלי שאין בפיו כשפופרת הנוד. gezeirah shelo yatbil machtin u'tsinorot bichli
she'ein be-piv kishfoferet hanod. We don't want you to immerse you know
pins and needles and other types of things that in a vessel
that does not have an opening the size of a tube this
tube of a flask. Are מחטין machtin and צנורות tsinorot
synonyms? Yeah I don't know what a צנור tsinor is a מחט
machet is a needle a צנור tsinor is some type of also
a small a small כלי.
And where does the שיעור shiur come from?
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai כדתנן Ked'tanan like we found in
a משנה Mishnah, what do they say there? Spinning hook spinning hook
okay. עירוב מקואות כשפופרת הנוד Eruv mikvaot kishfoferet hanod there's the idea
to combine right to combine מקואות mikvaot you need a you need
the hole be the size of a שפופרת הנוד shfoferet hanod of
this tube כעוביה וכחללה ke-ovya u-che-chalala like its width and like its
hollow like its cavity again I'm not exactly good with me what
עוביה ovya and חללה chalala are different but anyway presumably it means
all around.
Both sides but like let's say flat.
Right it means in both directions it means in both directions בשתי
אצבעות חוזרות למקומן bi-shtei etzbaot chozrot limkoman
to the width of two fingers you know that turn around so
meaning so basically meaning like a circle of a diameter of two
fingers.
Okay סבר לה Savar lah so
כהא דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה kahad'amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha fine so he
holds like the other version דאיכא אחד
עשר מעלות שנו כאן d'ika echar asar ma'alot shanu kan that the
claim that there are
eleven levels mentioned in the משנה Mishnah not ten because he doesn't
conflate the clothes with the vessels. So that means if you count
ten you don't hold this הלכה halacha in terms of...
No
because there are eleven no you don't know that that's the explanation
there are eleven so you only get ten by saying that the
one about the vessels and the one about the garments is really
a variation of the same and it's a חציצה concern so explaining
that this is not a חציצה concern makes it eleven keeps each
one distinct and gets you and keeps you at eleven and doesn't
let you get to ten. Okay now but nevertheless even though he
disagrees with that he agrees with the fundamental division into two groups.
שש ראשונות בין לקודש בין לחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש Shesh rishonot
bein le-kodesh bein le-chulin shena'asu al taharat ha-kodesh the first six apply
whether to actual things that are sanctified with the קדושה kedusha of
קרבנות korbanot or things like even חולין chulin if they're just given
treated as if they were קרבנות korbanot so these stringencies would apply
to them. אחרונות Achronot the last five לקודש אבל לא לחולין שנעשו
על טהרת הקודש le-kodesh aval lo le-chulin shena'asu al taharat ha-kodesh only
real things with real קדושה kedusha not with חולין that are that
are treated as if they have קדושה. kedusha. מאי איכא בין Mai
ika bein okay and for the same reason that the first five
have some more biblical concern associated. So now the גמרא Gemara so
that's whether you count eleven or ten but nevertheless everybody agrees that
the last five are in a separate category are less weighty a
little less weighty than the first five or six. Now we're going
to look at the difference between what difference it gives what reason
you give what difference it makes what reason you give between whether
it's a concern of a vessel of a חציצה or about this
concern about the pins and the needles and whatever. So מאי איכא
בין דרבא לדרב עילא Mai ika bein de-Rava le-de-Rav Ila what difference
does it make between רבא Rava and רב עילא Rav Ila which
reason you give? איכא בינייהו סל וגרגותני Ika beiniyeihu sal ve-gargutni
there's a difference between a basket and a other thing which is
like a large type of a basket like a woven basket. שמילאן
כלים והטבילן She'milan keilim ve-hitbilan
so you fill them with vessels and you immerse them think about
our case like I said in our כלים מקוה keilim mikva you
took one of those plastic laundry baskets imagine it was just made
out of hemp or something and you know and you filled it
with vessels and you dunked it. Is that a problem or not?
So למאן דאמר משום חציצה איכא Le-man d'amar mishum chatzitzah ika if
the problem is because of חציצה so that would be a problem
whatever the outer vessel is the inner vessel might weigh down again
we know water causes it to float good that's why it's not
a problem by תרומה truma, but by קודש kodesh we are more
stringent and that's relevant whether whatever type of outer
vessel it is even a like a big type of a basket
should be relevant. למאן דאמר משום גזרה שמא יטביל מחטין וצנורות Le-man
d'amar mishum gezeirah shema yatbil machtin u'tsinorot but if the concern is
about pins and
needles and You'll never find a basket that has a narrow opening.
The very nature of a something's identity as a basket is a
wide opening, right? That's one thing that makes it a basket. If
it didn't have a wide opening, it wouldn't be a basket; it'd
be a different type of a vessel. So therefore, somehow we categorically
exclude baskets from this גזרה. gezeirah. Things that are like, you know,
I don't know, pots and pans and other types of things, something
could still be a pot with a small opening, you know, and
you could have a tea kettle, and you could have those types
of things with small openings, but you don't have a basket with
a small opening, so that clearly would have been a category that
would have been excluded. Now by the way, it's interesting, you know,
because sometimes you hear that the גמרא Gemara says לא פלוג, lo
palug, you know, whatever the reason is that underlied a particular גזרה,
gezeirah, at the end of the day when we come to make
it, we don't start saying does it apply here, does it apply
there, we just say categorically you can never do it, right? But
of course, every now and then we do say that we are
going to make distinctions. It's easier to make distinctions when things can
be categories can be like lines can be divided, you know, drawn
between categories. It's not like every single vessel you'll bring to me
and I'll assess whether the גזרה gezeirah is relevant. That type of
thing we wouldn't do; that would be completely impossible to have a
system that would run by having to assess you know the each
each particular case whether the reason holds. But here we're not doing
that. We're saying you've got a category of vessels called baskets, which
the whole their whole definition as a basket is is that it
has a wide opening, right? So therefore for that category the גזרה
gezeirah never would have applied if the reason is the concern of
narrow you know of of vessels that have very narrow openings. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara would say would be a נפקא
מינה nafka mina between these two reasons. Okay so let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Now, דאזל רבא לטעמיה. de-azal Rava le-taimeih. Now רבא Rava goes
according to his reasoning, who this idea that it's about a concern
of the you know about the pins and needles in a vessel
with a narrow opening, דאמר רבא de-amar Rava because רבא Rava says,
סל הגרגוסטני שמילאן כלים והטבילן טהורים. sal ha-gargustani she-millan kelim ve-hitbilan tehorim.
If you have a basket that you filled with vessels and you
immersed them, then then it's טהור. tahor. Again, like we said, I
mean, you know, it's not a concern; it's a wide opening. Presumably
he means even for קודש. kodesh You know, certainly it's true for
everything else, but presumably the point is for all purposes, even for
קודש, kodesh? this is טהור tahor because the גזרה gezeirah did not
apply, the מעלה ma'alah did not apply because this is fundamentally a
vessel that has a wide opening. On that so there he's just
that's exactly what he said here; here he's spelling out that he
would hold by that practical application of his reason. Now here's another,
by the way, interesting ruling relating to this: ומקוה שחלקו בסל הגרגוסטני
הטובל שם לא עלתה לו טבילה. u-mikveh she-hillko be-sal ha-gargustani ha-tovel sham
lo alta lo tevilah. You had a forty סאה se'ah מקוה, mikveh,
you put in a מקוה mikveh whatever here let's say you put
here in your בור bor of מי השילוח Mei HaShiloach you put
a you put a
basket here okay I don't know we'll make it look like a
basket whatever it is okay but it's a wicker basket that it's
got a lot of you know it's got a lot of holes
so does that divide the מקוה? mikveh? Now you say you have
two מקוואות mikva'ot I know it doesn't look like a basket but
you get the idea you have two מקוואות mikva'ot of twenty סאה
se'ah or do you say give me a break there's all these
holes in the basket so you know of course it's going to
be one מקוה mikveh that doesn't create a division.
Why'd you put it in that side, not in the מקוה?
mikveh? Because this is the only כשר kosher מקוה mikveh here, this
is only כשר kosher because it connects to this. Ah so you
so it only would create a problem if it divided the real
מקוה. mikveh.
Okay so so
he says that that actually does divide the מקוה. mikveh. Now why
is that? Because he's why didn't you say that it's so totally
porous it's not considered a wall? So he says no, here's why
I'm not going to say that. דהארעא כולה חלחולי מחלחלה de-ara kullah
chalchulei mechalchalah because he says the whole earth is porous. Okay so
why don't I just say that any collection of water is connected
to forty סאה se'ah that exists somewhere underground and the whole earth
is porous and eventually water will rise up to the ground level?
I understand it's a very funny argument,
right? A type of a thing that it immediately runs from one
side to the other is a little different than stuff that over
I don't know even if it were days and certainly if it's
weeks and months takes for water to you know rise up through
the ground. The other question is, so what's the definition then? So
at what stage what would be let's say you made something that
was like I don't know you know by when you're making סוכות
sukkos you know you can make a wall by doing just like
three strings or like four strings like each one within like three
טפחים tefachim of another right? So if you had if you had
something like that and you had it to divide a מקוה mikveh
so halachically it's a מחיצה mechitzah right because it's got 2.9 טפחים
tefachim you know between each one and so on here whatever I
mean you have to do another one. Would that divide a מקוה
mikveh even though even though it was basically all open with just
a few strings? Once you say porous doesn't matter so is it
just a complete formal definition of a wall? Maybe it is, maybe
that's what רבא Rava seems to be saying, which is quite a
surprise, but that's but he doesn't seem to limit it like he
says I don't care that it's porous. If it applies to a
מחיצה, mechitzah, it should
apply to
something like this in the middle of a מקוה mikveh would be
considered to divide, right? By the way, you do see the emphasis
here that it's totally porous, it's got, it's sort of like exactly
like that laundry basket that we use, it's got major holes. That
might also be the reason why the גמרא Gemara says that the
גזירה gezeirah of a narrow opening doesn't apply because regardless of the
opening, it's a type of a thing that's a fundamentally a porous
vessel, a vessel that has a lot of holes in it. So
again, another reason that the גזירה gezeirah of a narrow opening should
not be relevant. Yes.
Does this mean it entirely separate the area? In other words,
what?
Oh, yes, good question. If the water was... no, no, no. If
the water went over, like this, right? Then the same way when
you've got a little opening, it can connect, right? Water that's running
on top of the surface of a wall can also connect the
two sides. Yes, that is a very, that is a good point.
So if the two large people are in the מקוה, mikveh, that's
still okay because...
Oh, you mean because then the people will cause the water to
rise up while they're in it?
No, no, no, because a person then couldn't divide a מקוה. mikveh.
Oh, oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But also that would
also be, but also on the sides as well. Yeah, but you're
saying if you've got a big fat large person in there or
whatever, he's
stopping up the water.
Right. Or I guess a very narrow מקוה mikveh or something like
that, right? Okay.
So how does this fit into the wicker basket part?
It doesn't, it's just a related issue about the basket.
Okay, actually that's not completely obvious because you might do גוד אסיק
gud asik for a מחיצה mechitzah in a מקוה. mikveh. What?
You might
cause it to...
I know, that's what I was saying. Okay, this actually gets discussed.
Okay, anyway, okay. והני מילי... ve-hani mili... where is it? אמר רב
פפא... amar Rav Papa... והני מילי ve-hani mili בכלי טהור, be-kli tahor,
אבל בכלי טמא, aval be-kli tamei,
now,
all these, this issue about the problem of a narrow opening in
the vessel is if the outer vessel was טהור. tahor. But if
the outer vessel was טמא, tamei, now this is interesting. It actually
becomes more lenient. מיגו דסלקא טבילה לכולה גופא דמנא, migu de-salka tevilah
le-kula gufa de-mana,
because the טבילה tevilah works for the outer vessel, for the whole
body of the vessel, the outer vessel, סלקא להו נמי לכלים דאית
בה. salka le-hu nami le-kelim de-it bah.
It also works for the vessels that are in it. Means, let's
read the case and then I'll spell it out. דתנן, di-tenan, because
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, כלים שמילאם כלים. kelim she-milam kelim.
Before I read the משנה, because the משנה's going to require a
little bit pre-explanation.
So let me tell you what that means.
So basically, here you go, here's your vessel, but it's a very
narrow opening. Now, and here's your little whatever, your needles. Okay, this
is טמא. tamei. So now water gets in here, okay? So water
gets in here,
but it's a very narrow opening. So it's not considered, like through
the... forget the vessel on the inside. You take your, you take
your, yes, it's less than a כשפופרת הנוד. ke-shfoferet ha-nod. Okay, but
nevertheless, even though it's less than a כשפופרת הנוד, ke-shfoferet ha-nod, so
it can't be considered like all part of the same מקוה mikveh
water, nevertheless you have to be able to טובל tovel, this vessel,
right? We can't say, oh, because this opening is so narrow, the
still the assumption is that the vessel you can still be טובל,
the water gets in here, and that's enough to say that it
was immersed in the מקוה, mikveh, even if we're going to say
that the water here is not part of the מקוה mikveh water,
one unit with the מקוה mikveh water, it was still fully immersed
in the מקוה mikveh and the water did get into it. Okay,
that would be that case. So then it would become טהור, tahor,
even with a very narrow opening. So now what we're saying is,
so now if in this טמא tamei vessel, when this טמא, tamei,
and you're going to dunk it in the מקוה, mikveh, you put
in your needles and so on, then the needles become טהור. tahor.
How did they become טהור? tahor? Not because they're considered to be
in the מקוה mikveh water. They're not in the מקוה mikveh water.
They're only in the vessel. But since the vessel is becoming טהור,
tahor, the status change that applies to the vessel also now applies
to anything that's inside of the vessel. So the needles became טהור
tahor without ever having been considered to be themselves immersed in the
מקוה mikveh water. They became טהור tahor because they were inside of
a vessel that was immersed, and when that vessel was changing its
status, the status change applied to the needles as well. I actually
thought once about using this as a solution to a problem that
comes up with a woman going to the מקוה mikveh who has
like a, like an ear infection, and or other types of things,
that and so you have to put something in the ear to
specifically, its job is to keep water out. So how do you
consider that not a חציצה if it's specifically there for the purpose
of keeping water out? And there are other types of scenarios like
that, things like casts or whatever, now it's less of an issue
with the fiberglass, but sometimes it is that things that absolutely cannot
get wet, so you have to put something on it to prevent
it from getting wet. So how do you not call that thing
a חציצה? So some of these issues have been addressed, like the
ear thing, there's a whole רב משה Reb Moshe תשובה teshuvah on
it, but some are not always so easy. So it occurred to
me, just, you'll think this is absurd, but okay, that what you
do is you create a, you create a vessel, although I don't
know, it might be too big to be considered a כלי, but
you create a vessel that that basically somebody can go into, okay?
And
I actually got two vessels, one in another, okay? So basically, so
the water and you immerse and you make this outer one טמא.
tamei. So the water goes here, this is טמא tamei and this
is טמא tamei and the woman is טמא. tamei. Okay, and then
you have to get wet at all, 'cause
you
immerse the whole thing in, here you have to be in an
inner vessel here or you'll get—you know what I'm saying? But the
inner one is also טמא, tamei, okay?
So the inner vessel and the woman, you know, are not—you know,
are like—are protected from the water. And since the טבילה tevilah works
for the outer vessel, it works for the woman and the water,
so you get to go to the מקוה mikvah without ever getting
wet. That was my idea. The only prob—A, I don't know that
we could say if just 'cause it works for vessels, it works
for people, although logically I don't see why not, but the other
question is that if you have a vessel that big, it might
not be considered a כלי. So we have to still figure out
if I can make that work, and then I have to get
someone to design it and make it. Yes.
Didn't we learn for earthenware vessels where we make the distinction between
the outside and the inside?
Well, earthenware vessels you can't be מטהר. metaher. So that's—in the מקוה
mikvah anyway. Okay.
So anyway, so that's—so in that case, you would not need there
to be a wide opening, you could have it become טהור tahor
without ever actually having been considered to have been in the מקוה
mikvah water,
because of what applies to the outer vessel. Okay, דתנן, ditnan, as
we taught in a משנה, כלים שמילאן כלים, kelim she-milan kelim, if
you fill vessels with vessels, והטפילן, vehitpilan, and you immerse them, הרי
אלו טהורים, harei elu tehorim, they're טהור. tahor. ואם לא טבל, ve-im
lo taval, and if you did not immerse them, מים המעורבין עד
שיהיו מעורבין כשפופרת הנוד, mayim ha-me'uravin ad she-ye-u me'uravin keshfoferet hano'ad,
then the water has to be combined like the size of this
tube. So what does that mean if you didn't immerse them, the
water has to be combined? That doesn't make any sense. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי קאמר mai ka'amar ואם לא טבל, ve-im lo
taval, what do you mean if you didn't immerse them? You can't
even—that doesn't make any sense. No, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, ואם אינו
צריך לטבילה, ve-im eino tzarich litvilah,
if they don't—if the outer one doesn't need to be immersed, meaning
if the outer one needed to be immersed because it was טמא,
tamei, then it'll automatically be מטהר metaher any vessel that's inside of
it. When the outer one becomes טהור, tahor, the inner one will
become טהור. tahor. That's if the outer one needed to be immersed.
But if the outer one did not need to be immersed, if
the outer one was טהור, tahor, מים המעורבין עד שיהיו מעורבין כשפופרת
הנוד, mayim ha-me'uravin ad she-ye-u me'uravin keshfoferet hano'ad, then the inner ones
only become טהור tahor if the water is connected by an opening
the size of this tube. So if again, you have these vessels
in a narrow—in a narrow-mouthed outer vessel, if the outer vessel needed
to go to the מקוה, mikvah, needed to be immersed, then it
works for the outer, it works for the inner. If the outer
one did not need to be immersed, it was טהור, tahor, it
only works for the inner if the opening is the size of
the שפופרת הנוד. shfoferet hano'ad. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara sort
of ends this point. דהא דרבא ורבי אילא, de-had de-Rava ve-Rabbi Ila,
this debate of רבא Rava and רבי אילא, Rabbi Ila, whether the
reason is חציצה or whether the reason is because of a concern
of a narrow opening, תנאי היא, tannai hi, is based on a
debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, ditnaya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita,
סל וגורגסני sal ve-gorgasni שמילאן כלים והטפילן, she-milan kelim ve-hitpilan, you again
took this big basket, wicker basket that you filled with vessels, בין
לקודש בין לתרומה, bein la-kodesh bein la-trumah, even for קודש kodesh. purposes
let alone for תרומה, truma, טהורים, tehorim, is fine. When you're dealing
with a basket, this level does not apply. אבא שאול, Abba Shaul,
that's like רבא. Rava. But then comes along אבא שאול אומר, Abba
Shaul omer, לתרומה אבל לא לקודש, la-trumah aval lo la-kodesh, no, that's
sorry, that's still the difference of levels still applies, that only works
for תרומה, truma not for קודש. So exactly this issue of basket
is debated, so it seems that the explanation is what is the
underlying reason. Is the reason like רבא, Rava, a concern of narrow-mouthed
vessels, or is the reason like רבי אילא, Rabbi Ila a concern
of one vessel weighing down on the other one? So the גמרא
Gemara now finally—so that's the two explanations. Now the גמרא Gemara looks
at the ברייתא, Baraita, it
doesn't give us these reasons.
Right, רבא Rava and רבי אילא gave us the reasons. Now the
גמרא Gemara gets around to saying, so, okay, these all seem legitimate
reasons, either one vessel will weigh down or there'll be a narrow
opening. So if it applies to קודש, it should apply to תרומה,
truma these are—this is a legitimate concern. Yes.
Just so I understand how far we go in הלכה. halachah. If
you have this very narrow vessel and you put it
in a מקוה mikvah
that is exactly 40 סאה, se'ah, and you're stuck, right?
Because if you take it out you have—you've popped liquid, now it's
less than that, even if you pour it back in, the water
would now be מים שאובים. mayim she'uvim. That might be, if it's
exactly 40 סאה. se'ah. You raise a good question, which is is
it possible with a narrow opening, the water would still not be
inside the vessel, would not be considered not part of the מקוה
mikvah to—to—to
reduce its 40 סאה se'ah minimum, but it wouldn't be considered enough—part—enough
one unit that something inside of it could still be considered being
immersed in the מקוה? mikvah? There's possible middle stages. But you're right,
it's possible in some scenarios it would be a problem, absolutely. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
okay, אי הכי i-hachi תרומה נמי, trumah nami, whatever the reason is,
whether it's the narrow mouth or whether it's weighing down, let it
be a concern for תרומה. truma So the גמרא Gemara says no,
למאן קאמרינן, le-man kamrinan, who's following these laws anyway of these different
levels? חברים, chaverim, they are—I mean חבר chaver is in context to
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, the people that are scrupulous about laws of
טהרה. taharah. So חברים ידעי, chaverim yadei, so חברים chaverim know the
laws and they'll be—make sure that one vessel isn't weighing down the
other or that the mouth is big enough. So the גמרא Gemara
says... That's true. אי הכי, i hachi, if you assume people know
the laws here, so קודש נמי, kodesh nami, so even by when
it's done for the purpose of קודש you shouldn't have this restriction.
So גמרא Gemara says no, there we're concerned חזי ליה עם הארץ
ואזיל מטביל. chazi lei Am Ha'aretz ve'azil matbil. No, we're concerned that
yes, you'll know what to do, but then the עם הארץ Am
Ha'aretz is going to follow your example, and then when he immerses
things for קודש, he'll do it also with one vessel in a
vessel, and he won't know what to be careful about and it'll
lead to problems. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but if we're
afraid that an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz is going to follow your
example, he'll follow your example by תרומות trumot also. So the גמרא
Gemara, says, so wait a minute, תרומה נמי חזי ליה עם הארץ
ואזיל מטביל. truma nami chazi lei Am Ha'aretz ve'azil matbil.
So תרומה truma, also he'll follow your example and he'll do what
you do for תרומה truma for his תרומה. truma גמרא says no,
there we have an answer. לא מקבלינן מינייהו. lo mikablinan mineihu. We
don't take תרומה truma from עם הארץ. Am Ha'aretz. If an עם
הארץ Am Ha'aretz comes to a חבר כהן chaver Kohen to give
him תרומה, truma. he'll say why don't you give it to your
friend the כהן עם הארץ, Kohen Am Ha'aretz, don't give it to
me. Okay, which is lovely which it again gets to this issue
of creating these you know divisions in society. So okay, he might
actually you know you know sort of you
know misunderstand copy us in an incorrect way and it'll lead to
him not being careful by תרומה, truma but it's not it won't
affect us because we're not going to eat the תרומה truma he's
going to give us. So why are we not concerned that he'll
also follow our example by how to deal with things for קודש
and you know so I'm sorry. So therefore excuse me, so I'm
so so so then for by קודש also why why do we
have to have this higher level? You know let's just say we
won't accept קרבנות korbanot from him. But obviously there's a big difference.
תרומה truma we can tell him give it to another כהן who's
an עם הארץ כהן. Am Ha'aretz Kohen. We I you know I
the כהן חבר Kohen chaver won't take it. But if he comes
with a קרבן, korban, we can't say what bring it in your
own בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, there's only one בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Okay, so that's why we have to we can't we have to
be careful that he doesn't follow our we don't have to be
so careful he doesn't follow our example by תרומה truma because we're
able to keep these divisions of practice around תרומה, truma. but by
קרבנות korbanot and קדשים kodshim where we can't keep divisions of practice,
we have to be very he's going to look at us what
we do and we're when we handle things for קרבנות korbanot. purpose
and he'll follow that example presumably he knows enough to know that
there'd be different standards between תרומה truma. and קרבנות. korbanot So he'll
be very careful to focus on what example we're setting in this
קרבנות korbanot. area and follow that. And there we have to be
very careful to set the right example because we'll have no way
that we can say don't we're not going to accept what you're
bringing to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yes.
Isn't something in respect to דמאי demai is based on the principle
that עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz are trusted with תרומה truma but aren't
trusted with מעשר?
Yes, but that's when you're not receiving the תרומה truma. from them.
That's when you're receiving the grain from them and you assume that
they've removed the תרומה. truma, Okay, so then you can assume that
it has the תרומה truma removed so you can eat the grain.
But that's different than the עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz coming and saying
here's the תרומה Mr. כהן please take this and that you're expected
to eat it.
Yes. What קודש are we talking about these vessels?
An animal it can't be. No, that's what I said before wine
and oil are the most obvious example. It could also be a
מנחה mincha or wine and oil for the נסכים nesachim that goes
with a קרבן, right.
Okay, but when you buy the wine at the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash there you still put it in your vessel.
Yeah,
and you don't have to buy it at the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash there although you're right that is normally what's done. Okay, so
that's the גמרא's answer. Okay, and also again fascinating that you know
you'd think he's an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz he's not so aware.
A it's not even visible. Are you dunking the thing in the
מקוה mikvah for תרומה or for קודש? You gotta know a lot
to understand you know A just to have information like you know
visually thing something won't tell you why it's being dunked. And you
have to know enough to realize that there might be different standards
hearing for one or the other. Right, to the point that the
גמרא can say the עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz will look at what
we're doing for תרומה and maybe be misled but we don't care
because they'll just follow it in terms of how they handle תרומה.
But we can't let them be misled but then they'll look at
what we're doing for קודש and we have to make sure there
they're not misled. But they're going to follow a distinct example that
we set for קודש in terms of how they handle קודש which
to me seems a little bit hard to imagine. But okay. So
let's take a look. So גמרא says like this. קודש נמי לא
נקבלי מינייהו. kodesh nami lo nekabel mineihu. So okay, why should we
care what example we set for קודש? Let's not accept you know
the stuff they bring for us in their vessels that are קרבנות.
korbanot So הוי ליה איבה. havei lei eiva. No, there'll be enmity.
They'll say ah you're not accepting my stuff. So תרומה נמי הוי
ליה איבה. truma nami havei lei eiva. So there's enmity by תרומה.
We're not accepting oh we're not good enough for you by the
תרומה you won't take our תרומה. לא אכפת ליה דאזיל יהיב ליה
לכהן עם הארץ. lo ichpat lei de'azil yahiv lei le'Kohen Am Ha'aretz.
Nah, he's
there's not so much enmity. All right, he won't take my תרומה,
I'll give it to another of my friend the כהן עם הארץ.
Kohen Am Ha'aretz. Yeah, as if that won't cause any איבה. eiva.
Like you're not good enough for you, but good enough for one
of my friends. Anyway, but at least it'll be at least somebody
will take his תרומה so it won't lead to so much איבה.
eiva. But ומאן תנא דחייש לאיבה, u'man tana dechaish le'eiva, but by
קרבנות korbanot? it's a different story. There's nothing else he can do
with it and he's being completely rejected. Okay, and now the גמרא
spells that out. ומאן תנא דחייש לאיבה, u'man tana dechaish le'eiva, which
is the תנא tanna that's concerned by איבה eiva for עם הארץ
Am Ha'aretz specifically around קרבנות? korbanos, רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. It's רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא braita אמר
רבי יוסי מפני מה הכל נאמנים על טהרת יין ושמן... amar Rabbi
Yossi mipnei mah hakol ne'emanim al taharat yayin veshemen... בשמן כל ימות
השנה, veshemen kol yemot hashanah, why are people believed for the purity
of wine and oil all the days throughout the year, meaning there
are times, maybe specific times during the רגל regel where people are
believed about everything? That's what we're getting up to. But when somebody
brings wine and oil to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash at any
time, not even the רגל regel during the year, we assume it's
טהור. tahor. And by the way, notice the irony, right? We have
all of these מעלות, maalos, we have all of these things, but
all of a sudden somebody's coming to bring the holiest thing to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and we completely just accept their trustworthiness
on it, right? So it's quite fascinating how it completely undermines all
these things, and it's similar to the idea of the רגל, regel,
of the way of really the need of not
creating really a completely separate class of people. So why is everybody
believed when they bring wine and oil to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash any time in the year? כדי שלא יהא כל אחד ואחד
הולך ובונה במה לעצמו. Kedei shelo yehei kol echad ve'echad holech uvoneh
bamah le'atzmo. Because if you don't accept them in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and they're going to want to bring קרבנות, what are
they going to do? They'll build their own little במה, bamah, their
own little altar in their backyard. "Oh, you won't take mine in
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Fine, I'll bring it. I'll make my
own altar." The פרה אדומה Parah Adumah one: "I'm not טהור tahor
enough for you? Fine, I'll bring my own פרה אדומה." Parah Adumah.
So you don't want to sort of do the types of things
that are going to reject people to the point that they basically
feel like they're going to go off on their own and do
their own thing. And it's
very interesting thinking about this in terms of contemporary realities, about how
much what type of divisions do we make amongst כלל ישראל Klal
Yisrael that make people feel that they have no connection to certain
segments of the people? Fine, we'll go just go do our own
thing. And this is even a במה לעצמו bamah le'atzmo to the
גד gad level, let alone that they might go worship in who
knows what type of a temple. So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Pappa, so there's only one בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so you better
do what you need to do to make people feel like they
have a place in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Pappa, and therefore if we're going to do that anyway,
we've got to be careful to be setting the right standards. So
it's one thing to trust them, but at least we have to
present the right standards to at least make it better. Then we'll
assume that they have maybe can trust them to have followed it.
And therefore we have to be more careful by קודש. אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, let's just wrap
this up: כמאן מקבלינן האידנא סהדותא מעם הארץ? keman mekablilan idna sahadusa
mi'am ha'aretz?
According to what approach do we accept testimony nowadays from an עם
הארץ? am ha'aretz? Normally עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, besides תרומה וטהרה, terumah
vetaharah, were considered to be generally certainly less scholarly, but maybe also
in some ways less careful about
either honesty or less careful about paying attention to the things they
needed to pay attention to in order to be considered as legitimate
witnesses. And so nowadays we do accept them as witnesses. Who does
that follow? כמאן? Keman? כרבי יוסי, Ke'Rabbi Yose, like רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, who says that this concern of איבה eivah is a very
dominant concern and lets us override other types of reasons that we
would reject עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. So in the time of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, rejection means you're not accepted from the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What are the areas of rejection nowadays that we
are most sensitive to? So somebody that can't even be a trusted
witness in a court is a really a way of basically completely
rejecting a person. So we have to override that law so that
does not lead to a sense of complete rejection. And again what
you're seeing here is an amazing thing. So on the one hand
the משניות are making all of these different levels, but like today's
דף, daf, I mean we're עמוד amud ahead, but anyway the עמוד
amud today ends with a point that you could have radical
different, you can have these concerns about all of these areas, but
if there's this issue that they're going to basically completely feel rejected
and maybe completely lead to a split, then you override all those
concerns. So even in something as weighty as the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash or as serious as testimony, and we're not limiting it to
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the importance is now we're extending it. So
again, when you get to the rabbinic period, all these issues of
עם הארץ am ha'aretz and these multiple levels or whatever, most of
them have faded in the background. I mean, sure there are discussions
in the גמרא, but they tend to really be historical discussions. The
reality of it has basically faded in the background, partly because there's
no מקדש Mikdash and טומאה וטהרה tuma v'taharah concerns are less, but
partly also because the same thing that we're going to get to
in the end by the רגל, regel, a desire to create unity,
here you're seeing other types of things that are pushing
to say what is the cost of these types of distinctions and
to be real and sometimes the cost is much too big to
be paid. Do you want to say something?
No, it's just the paradigm here is located in the two institutions
around which Jewish life was organized, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
the בית דין. Beis Din. Right.
Although it is interesting that again I don't know if without the
example of the עדות eidus I would have said בית דין Beis
Din would have been my obvious thing. I mean I would tend
to say the בית המדרש Beis Hamedrash and תורה, Torah, or maybe
בית הכנסת Beis Haknesses and so on. But yes, I mean I
think
that's where like עמך Amcha feels like everybody's got to get to.
That's true, that is true. Okay, so great, so we'll end here.
All right, good, so we're עמוד amud ahead, so we should be
able to not have to do it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and still
be, like, today on.